Guide to the Augustus Welby Northmore Pugin Drawings
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Augustus Welby Northmore Pugin drawings.
1833-1851
OSB MSS 66
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
4.02
(4 boxes)
63 pencil, pen and ink, and wash drawings, signed, of buildings and architectural details, sculpture, and other subjects, chiefly in France, Northern Germany and Antwerp.
Pugin, Augustus Welby Northmore, 1812-1852
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from James Mackey in 1995 on the James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn Collection Fund. Osborn Accession 95.3.3.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
AUGUSTUS WELBY NORTHMORE PUGIN (1812-1852)
Augustus Welby Northmore Pugin (1812-1852), English architect, designer and author, was a leading figure in the Gothic Revival and the Oxford Movements. His designs include St. Chad's Cathedral, Birmingham, Balliol College, Oxford, and St. Augustine's Church, Ramsgate. His True Principles of Pointed or Christian Architecture (1841) inspired John Ruskin. During his last years he worked with Sir Charles Barry on the new Palace of Westminster. Pugin died in London on September 14, 1852.
Scope and Contents
The Osborn Collection of drawings by Augustus Welby Northmore Pugin (1812-1852) is listed according to the catalog numbers given in the Catalogue of the Drawings Collection of the Royal Institute of British Architects: The Pugin Family, by Alexandra Wedgwood. Brief descriptions are provided in this list: for full details, see the Wedgwood catalogue.
Many of the drawings have been rematted for exhibition use, as a result of which they are stored according to size. The list of drawings is arranged in Wedgwood number order, with the box location of each drawing indicated to the left of each entry.
Church Buildings -- Europe -- Pictorial works; Drawings (visual works); Pugin, Augustus Welby Northmore, 1812-1852; Cathédrale Notre-Dame (Rouen, France) -- Pictorial works; Cathédrale Saint-Pierre (Beauvais, France) -- Pictorial works; Koninklijk Museum voor Schone Kunsten (Belgium) -- Pictorial works
- Ramsgate, The Grange: View of the Oratory, from the door looking East. Pencil & wash, 1849 (Box 3, Folder [60.2])
- Ramsgate, The Grange: View of the Passage and Staircase outside the Oratory. Pencil & wash, 1849 (Box 1, Folder [60.3])
- Antwerp, Royal Museum of Fine Arts: Angel of the Annunciation by Simone Martini. Pen & watercolor, n.d. (Box 1, Folder [112.1])
- Antwerp, Royal Museum of Fine Arts: Lectern, morse, cup with hinged lid, and priest celebrating Mass before altar... from the triptych of the seven sacraments by Roger van der Weyden. Pen, 1842 (Box 2, Folder [112.2])
- Antwerp, Royal Museum of Fine Arts: Kneeling, censing angel & banderole from panel of the Benediction formerly attributed to Justus van Gent. Pen (Box 1, Folder [112.3])
- Antwerp, Royal Museum of Fine Arts: The Holy Women at the Tomb by Gerard David, with studies of heads to larger scale. Pen & watercolor, 1833 (Box 1, Folder [112.4])
- Antwerp, Royal Museum of Fine Arts: Head of Virgin from panel by Quentin Massys, with details of left eye & edging of cloak. Pen, n.d. (Box 1, Folder [112.5])
- Antwerp, Royal Museum of Fine Arts: Kneeling abbot from right-hand panel of diptych by "Bruges Master of 1499," with details. Watercolor & pen (Box 3, Folder [112.7])
- Antwerp, Royal Museum of Fine Arts: Seated Virgin from Calvary by Antonella da Messina, with details including canopy from panel by Master of Hoogstraeten, [n.d.] (Box 1, Folder [112.8])
- Antwerp, Royal Museum of Fine Arts: Standing figure of St. Paul from fresco by Bicci di Lorenzo, flying angel holding cloth canopy from painting of standing Virgin by Jan van Eyck, kneeling nun from panel of Christ before the Crucifixion by follower of Cornelius Engelbrechts, and cusping from portrait of an unknown canon by Memling. Watercolor & pen (Box 1, Folder [112.9])
- Louvain, Church of St. Peter: Studies of crozier and cross from wings of triptych by Dieric Bouts. Pen (Box 3, Folder [113])
- Namur, Convent of Les Soeurs de Notre- Dame: General view, studies of a lecturn, studies of a ring and a foot reliquary. Pen (Box 3, Folder [114])
- Amiens, Cathedral: View of North transept facade & North side of nave. Pencil, 1836 (Box 3, Folder [115.1])
- Amiens, Church of St. Germain: View of portal. Pencil, 1836 (Box 3, Folder [116])
- Amiens, Church of St. Leu: View of West front from street, with towers of cathedral in background. Pencil, 1836 (Box 1, Folder [117])
- Amiens: View of facade and tower of late Gothic parish church. Pencil, 1836 (Box 1, Folder [118])
- Beauvais, Cathedral: Exterior of chevet. Pencil, 1836 (Box 2, Folder [119.1])
- Beauvais, Cathedral: Facade of North transept. Pencil, 1836 (Box 2, Folder [119.2])
- Beauvais, Cathedral: 14th century Clock in North transept. Pen & pencil, 1847 (Box 3, Folder [119.3])
- Beauvais: View of street with timber- framed houses looking towards gateway. Pen (Box 1, Folder [120])
- Blois: View of medieval street crossed by enclosed wooden bridge. Pen, 1847 (Box 1, Folder [121])
- Bourges, Hotel Cujas: View of courtyard. Pencil, 1851 (Box 1, Folder [122])
- Evreux, Cathedral: Pulpit seen across nave. Watercolor, 1837 (Box 1, Folder [124.1])
- Evreux, Cathedral: North transept rose window & triforium. Watercolor, 1837 (Box 1, Folder [124.2])
- Gisors, Church of St. Gervais: View of West front. Pencil, 1836 (Box 2, Folder [125.1])
- Gisors, Church of St. Gervais: Chevet from Southeast. Pencil, 1836 (Box 2, Folder [125.2])
- Honfleur: View of shore and ships. Pencil, 1836 (Box 3, Folder [126])
- Noyon, Cathedral: 17th century tomb slab of priest, with details. Pen over pencil, 1851 (Box 1, Folder [127.1])
- Noyon, Cathedral: 15th century tomb slab of priest, with details. Pen over pencil, 1851 (Box 1, Folder [127.2])
- Paris, Church of St. Gervais & St. Protais: Interior view of axial chapel, showing altar with high reredos. Pencil, 1836 or 37 (Box 2, Folder [128])
- (4 drawings in one mat, numbered 1 through 4) Poitiers, Ducal Palace & Hotel de la Prevote: part-plans, external elevations, view from street, and details of statuary, tracery, moldings, etc. Pen, 1847 (Box 4, Folder [129])
- Rouen, Cathedral: S. transept looking South in West aisle, with kneeling figures. Watercolor, 1837 (Box 1, Folder [130.1])
- Rouen, Cathedral: North transept East aisle. Watercolor, 1837 (Box 1, Folder [130.2])
- Rouen, Church of St. Andre-aux-Febres: View of choir & tower from street looking Northwest. Pencil, [1836 or 37] (Box 1, Folder [131])
- Rouen, Church of St. Maclou: View of North transept rose window and triforium. Watercolor, 1836 or 37 (Box 2, Folder [132])
- Rouen, Church of St. Patrice: View in North aisle. Watercolor, 1837 (Box 4, Folder [133])
- Rouen, Museum of Antiquities: Studies of medieval metalwork. Pen & watercolor, 1836 or 37 (Box 4, Folder [135])
- Rouen, Rue des Moulins: View showing tall timber-framed houses. Pencil, 1836 or 37 (Box 1, Folder [136])
- Rouen: View of narrow street with tall timber-framed houses. Pencil, 1836 or 37 (Box 1, Folder [137])
- Rouen: View of tall timber-framed house on street corner. Pencil, 1836 or 37 (Box 4, Folder [138])
- Villeneuve-les-Avignon, Porte St. Andre: View of entrance. Sepia wash, 1847 (Box 1, Folder [140])
- Cologne, Cathedral & Church of St. Ursula: Studies from stained glass windows. Pen & watercolor, 1845 (Box 4, Folder [141])
- Cologne, Cathedral & Church of St. Ursula: Studies of a standing figure of St. Sebastian from a stained glass window in the cathedral, and of a stone statue of St. Ursula in the church of St. Ursula, with part-plans and details of pedestal. Pen, watercolor, & wash, 1845 (Box 2, Folder [142])
- Cologne, Cathedral & Church of St. Ursula: Studies from stained glass windows, reliquary busts, and a metal crucifixion group. Pen & watercolor, 1845 (Box 4, Folder [143])
- Cologne: Views of church of Klein St. Martin and of an unidentified church. Pen (Box 4, Folder [144])
- Freiburg-im-Breisgau, Cathedral: Studies of Stained Glass. Pen & watercolor over pencil, 1845 (Box 2, Folder [145])
- Luebeck, Cathedral: Plans, elevations, & details of late Gothic chandelier decorated with seated figures of bishops and angels. Pen, 1850 (Box 2, Folder [146])
- Luebeck, Cathedral: Study of the tomb effigy of Bishop Heinrich von Bockholt, with details of costume and frame. Pen (Box 2, Folder [147])
- Nuremberg, Deer park gate: View from Bergstrasse. Sepia wash, 1838 (Box 2, Folder [149])
- Ulm, Cathedral: View of choir stalls. Sepia wash & pencil, 1838 (Box 1, Folder [151])
- View of unidentified church on cliff overlooking the Rhine. Sepia & blue wash, 1844 (Box 4, Folder [152])
- Baslow: View of 3-arched medieval bridge. Pen & pencil, n.d. (Box 1, Folder [153])
- Gedney, Church of St. Mary Magdalen: Studies of 15th century tracery and 14th century porch arch. Pen (Box 1, Folder [155])
  Scope and Contents
  Housed in mat with [156]
- Shrewsbury, Church of St. Mary: Studies of flowing tracery and stained glass. Pen (Box 1, Folder [156])
  Housed in mat with [155]
- Distant view of tall ruins on a hill with houses in foreground. Watercolor, [before 1836?] (Box 1, Folder [158])
- Basle, Church of St. Martin: View from Southeast, with medieval conduit in foreground. Pencil, 1845 (Box 4, Folder [159])
- Basle: Street scene with late Gothic houses. Pencil, 1845 (Box 1, Folder [160])
- Fribourg: View of street and church with tall needle spire, with church on hilltop in background. Sepia wash, [1844?] (Box 2, Folder [161])
- Lucerne: Street scene with old houses and canal. Pencil, [1847?] (Box 1, Folder [162.1])
- Lucerne: View inside Hofbruecke. Pencil, [1847?] (Box 1, Folder [162.2])